Guide to the Albert William Sherer, Jr. papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Albert William Sherer, Jr. papers
1947-1988
MS 1487
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7
(7 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, background files, notebooks, photographs, and audio tapes, which document Albert William Sherer's career in the Foreign Service. The papers include the notebooks Sherer kept as ambassador to the Republic of Guinea and numerous files concerning the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe and the Helsinki Accords.
Sherer, Albert William, 1916-1986
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Carroll R. Sherer, 1988.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Albert William Sherer was born on January 16, 1916, in Wheaton, Illinois. He graduated from Yale University in 1938 and from Harvard Law School in 1941. Sherer joined the Foreign Service in 1946 and served in various assignments in Morocco, Hungary, Poland, Togo, Guinea, and Czechoslovakia. In 1974 Sherer headed the United States delegation to the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe and drafted the human rights provisions which were ratified as part of the Helsinki Accords in 1975. Sherer died in Chicago, Illinois, on December 27, 1986.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, background files, notebooks, photographs, and audio tapes, which document Albert William Sherer's career in the Foreign Service. The papers include the notebooks Sherer kept as ambassador to the Republic of Guinea and numerous files concerning the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe and the Helsinki Accords.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged chronologically according to Sherer's appointments or positions.
Diplomacy; Human rights; Czechoslovakia; Guinea; Hungary; Poland; Togo; United States -- Foreign relations -- Czechoslovakia; United States -- Foreign relations -- Guinea; United States -- Foreign relations -- Hungary; United States -- Foreign relations -- Poland; United States -- Foreign relations -- Togo; Ambassadors; Sherer, Albert William, 1916-1986; United States. Foreign Service; Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe
- Inventory
  - Budapest - second secretary and consul (1949 May-1951 Jul)
    - Materials concerning Groesz trial (Box 1)
    - Printed material concerning Hungarian political trials (Box 1)
    - Printed material concerning Soviet takeover of Eastern Europe, 1954-1956 (Box 1)
  - Prague - chief of combined Political/Economic Section (1955 Jan-1957 Jun)
    - Materials, including Sherer's handbook, Moscow's European Satellites, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Printed materials on communism in Eastern Europe, 1947-1956 (Box 2)
  - Department of State - Bureau of Eastern European Affairs, Polish Desk (1957 Sep-1960 Jul)
    - Materials concerning visit of Richard Nixon, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Center for International Affairs, Harvard University fellow (1960 Sep-1961 Jul)
    - Sherer's paper (Box 2)
  - Republic of Togo - ambassador (1967 Sep-1970 Jan); ambassador to Republic of Equatorial Guinea (1968 Oct-1970 Jan)
    - Personal files, photographs, clippings, correspondence (Box 2)
  - Republic of Guinea - ambassador (1970 Mar-1972 Jan)
    - Briefing books, background material, notebooks, personal files (Box 3)
    - Printed matter (including autographed volume by Sékou Touré and issues of Jeune Afrique ), audio tapes (Box 4)
  - Czechoslovak Socialist Republic - ambassador (1972 Feb-1975 Jul)
    - Personal files, background files, correspondence (Box 4)
  - Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe (CSCE, later known as Helsinki Accords) - chief of U. S. delegation (1974 Feb-1975 Jul)
    - Log, background material (Box 4)
    - Press files, background files (Box 5)
  - United Nations - deputy U.S. representative to the Security Council (1975 Aug-1977 Apr)
    - Log, correspondence, photographs, file on murder of Francis Meloy (ambassador to Lebanon) (Box 5)
  - U.S. delegation returning the Crown of St. Stephen to Budapest (1977 Jan)
    - Briefing book, press kit (Box 5)
  - CSCE first follow-up, Belgrade - chief of U.S. delegation to the Preparatory Conference (1977 Jun-Aug) and deputy chief of U.S. delegation to the follow-up (1977 Oct-1978 Mar)
    - Preparatory, background files, instructions, letters, proposals (Box 5)
    - Log, basic documents, press reports, congressional testimony (Box 6)
  - Seven Springs Center (Yale University) - diplomat in residence (1978-1979)
    - Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Retired from Foreign Service (1978-1979)
    - Subject files: arms control; detente; Foreign Policy Magazine; Poland; Post Helsinki (CSCE) and Madrid; Soviet talk; U.S. policy on human rights, 1980-1988 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter (Box 7)